You have learned how to incorporate velocity and yaw
你已经学会了如何把速度和
rate measurements into the particle filter.
角速度测量值纳入粒子滤波器
But what about sensor measurements, such as readings
但是 传感器测量值 比如
from radar or lidar?
雷达或激光雷达读数怎么办？
These landmark measurements will be
这些地标测量值会被用于
used to compute the update step, which you saw before
计算更新步骤 在前面的贝叶斯滤波器
in the Bayesian filter.
课程中我们学习过
Instead of the feature measurements directly affecting
在这里 特征测量值不会直接影响
the prediction of the state of the car,
车辆的状态预测
the measurements will instead inform
相反 测量值会告知
the weight of each particle.
每个粒子的权重
The size of each particle in this visualization
在该可视化中 每个粒子的大小
correlates with its weight.
与其权重相关
One way to update the weights of the particles
更新粒子权重的一种方法
is to use the multivariate Gaussian probability density
是对每个测量值使用
function for each measurement and combine
多变量高斯概率分布 然后
the likelihoods of all the measurements
取所有测量值概率的成绩
by taking their product.
计算合并概率
This function tells us how likely
这个函数告诉我们
a set of landmark measurements is given our predicted state
在给定车辆状态、并假设传感器
of the car and the assumption that the sensors have
有高斯噪时 一组地标测量值
Gaussian noise.
出现的概率
We also assume each landmark measurement is independent,
我们还假设 每个地标测量值都是独立的
so we will take the product of the likelihoods
因此 我们取所有测量值
over all measurements.
可能性的乘积
Here, xi represents the ith landmark measurement
这里 Xi 代表一个特定粒子的
for one particular particle.
第 i 个地标测量值
mu i represents the predicted measurement
μi 代表第 i 个测量值对应的
for the map landmark corresponding
地图地标的
to the ith measurement.
预测测量值
m is the total number of measurements for one particle.
m 是一个粒子的测量值总数
And finally, sigma is the covariance of the measurement.
最后 Σ 是测量值的协方差
The covariance matrix sigma is a symmetric square matrix
协方差矩阵 Σ 是对称方矩阵
that contains the variance, or uncertainty,
包括了传感器测量值中每个变量的
of each variable in the sensor measurement,
方差 或不确定性
as well as the covariance, or correlation,
以及这些变量之间的
between these variables.
协方差 或关联
In the case of lidar, the variables in question
对激光雷达而言 涉及的变量
would be the x and y position of the landmark
为地标和车辆坐标的
and vehicle coordinates.
X 和 y 位置
The diagonal terms of the covariance matrix
协方差矩阵的对角线项
are the variance of each variable,
是每个变量的方差
which is the standard deviation of the variable squared.
即变量平方后的标准差
Here, the orange ovals around each lidar measurement
这里 每个橙色激光雷达测量值周围的橙色椭圆
are geometric representations of some covariance matrices.
都是一些协方差矩阵的几何呈现
Notice how the covariance changes as you
注意对角线项改变时
change the diagonal terms.
协方差如何变更
As the x variance term increases,
随着 x 方差项的增加
the uncertainty in the x direction also increases.
在 x 方向的不确定性也会增加
Note that feature measurements are usually
注意 特征测量值通常以
given in vehicle coordinates, where
车辆坐标的形式给出
the x-axis points in the direction of the car's heading
其中 x 轴指向车辆航向
and the y-axis points to the left of the car.
y 轴指向车辆左侧
Similarly, as the y variance term increases,
同样地 随着 y 方差项的增加
the uncertainty in the y direction also increases.
在 y 方向的不确定性也会增加
You can think of the covariance matrix
你可以把协方差矩阵
as an inverse matrix of weights.
看作权重矩阵的逆
The smaller the diagonal term for a certain variable,
对某个特定变量 对角线项越小
the more you can trust this variable in the measurement
该变量在测量中的可信度越高
and the higher the weight we can put on it.
我们可以赋予的权重就越大
The off diagonal terms of the covariance matrix
协方差矩阵的非对角线项
represent the correlation between the two variables.
代表连个变量之间的关联
For instance, if x increases as y increases,
例如 如果 x 随着 y 的增加而增加
you could represent that in the off diagonal terms
你可以在矩阵的非对角线项中
of this matrix.
呈现出来
For the project, we will assume the different variables
对于这个实战项目 我们假定传感器测量值
in the sensor measurement are independent,
中的不同变量是独立的
and therefore the off diagonal terms are 0.
因此 非对角线项是 0
However, this is often not the case in practice.
但是 实践中情况往往不一样
Here is a geometric representation
这里是带有非对角线项的
of some covariance matrices with off diagonal terms.
一些协方差矩阵的几何呈现
Notice how the ovals look different from the covariances
注意这些椭圆形和之前的协方差不一样
before that only had non-zero diagonal terms.
之前的协方差只包括非零的对角线项
They now show a positive or negative correlation
现在 x 和 y 之间呈现出
between x and y.
正或负相关
Awesome.
太棒了
After you update the weights for each particle,
更新每个粒子的权重后
you will have to resample the particles with probability
你需要对概率和这些权重成正比的粒子
proportional to these weights, as was discussed
重采样 我们前一节课
in the previous lesson.
讨论过
And then you're done.
这样 我们就搞定了
Next, you'll learn about how to evaluate
接下来 一旦你成功创建了
the accuracy of your particle filter
自己的粒子滤波器 你需要学习
once you've successfully built it.
如何评估其准确度